Guide to the United House of Prayer for All People collection, 1944-1955 MS2231
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
United House of Prayer for All People collection
1944-1955
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MS2231
0.5 Linear Feet
This collection contains magazines and jewelry related to the history of the United House of Prayer for All People, the founder Bishop C.M. Grace (Sweet Daddy Grace) and Bishop Walter McCollough (Daddy McCollough).
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
For most of this material the acquisition information is not available and it may have come in over time for various sources. Most of the jewelry was a gift of Marie Dallam, 2007 (Accession 2007.055).
Historical or Biographical Note
The United House of Prayer for All People is a Church founded from the Pentecostal movement by Charles Manuel Grace (Marcelino Manuel da Graca) (1882?-1960), who proclaimed himself as "Bishop" in 1919. Marcelino Manuel da Graca was born in Brava Verde in the Cape Verde Islands. C. M. Grace was known as Sweet Daddy Grace. Following his death in 1960, Walter McCollough assumed the position of Bishop. He died in 1991 after which the current Bishop S.C. Madison assumed the role of Church leader.
In 1919 Bishop Grace built the first United House of Prayer For All People in West Wareham, Massachusetts, and incorporated the United House of Prayer for All People in Washington, D.C. in 1927. As of 2007, The United House of Prayer for All People has over 100 places of worship in 23 states. The National Headquarters for the church is located in Washington, D.C. As seen on the Church's website the purpose of the organization is "... to establish maintain and perpetuate the doctrine of Christianity and the Apostolic Faith throughout the world among all people; To erect and maintain houses of prayer and worship where all people may gather for prayer and to worship the Almighty God in spirit and in truth, irrespective of denomination or creed, and to maintain the Apostolic Faith of the Lord and Savior Jesus Christ."
The headquarters located at 601 M Street NW is listed as a site in the Cultural Tourism DC African American Trail database. The description of the church includes the following "One of the first United House of Prayer churches opened in 1929 at 601 M Street, NW. It joined a number of storefront churches born during the Great Depression (1929-1939). Grace's theology was based on the teachings of Jesus Christ and the Old Testament, as well as the power of the Holy Ghost. Grace was a charismatic leader who amassed a great fortune. Many of his followers joined the church while experiencing one of the many revivals and baptisms that Grace offered throughout the country. He was known for his flamboyant style, evidenced by his green and purple coats with gold trimmings, his long fingernails painted red, white, and blue, and his flowing hair. During the 1950s, he lived at 11 Logan Circle, NW. Bishop Walter McCullough succeeded Grace. Under his leadership, the church built low-rent housing projects throughout the city, including McCullough Canaanland Apartments, Paradise Gardens, and McCullough Haven for senior citizens, all in the Shaw neighborhood. "
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains jewelry, portraits, magazines, and ephemera related to the United House of Prayer for All People and Bishops C.M. Grace, known as Sweet Daddy Grace and Walter McCollough, known as Daddy McCollough. The Grace Magazine and House of Prayer Quarterly include Bible study and numerous testimonials of the healing capabilities of Sweet Daddy Grace. All the pieces of jewelry have images of either Daddy Grace or Daddy McCollough. The material dates from 1944-55 although the jewelry and portraits are not dated.
Collection Organization
Organized into two series: Papers and Jewelry
Religion; Washington (D.C.); African American Pentacostal churches; United House of Prayer for All People; Grace, Daddy; McCollough, W.
- Papers, 1944-1955; MS2231 Series 1; 0.5 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains magazines produced by the House of Prayer for All people including Grace Magazine and House of Prayer Quarterly, magazine articles about the church and Sweet Daddy Grace, two portraits of Sweet Daddy Grace, and several pieces of ephemera including ribbons, stamps with Sweet Daddy Grace's portrait, and two labels for soap products produced by the House of Prayer. These materials date from 1944-55 although there are no dates for a portion of the items.
  - Grace magazine, 08/1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Grace magazine, 12/1952 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - House of Prayer Quarterly Vol. 3 No. 3, 07/1944-09/1944 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - House of Prayer Quarterly Vol. 11 No. 2, 04/1952-06/1952 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - House of Prayer Quarterly Vol. 11 No. 3, 07/1952-09/1952 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - House of Prayer Quarterly Vol. 12 No. 1, 01/1953-03/1953 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - House of Prayer Quarterly Vol. 12 No. 3, 07/1953-09/1953 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - House of Prayer Quarterly Vol. 12 No. 4, 10/1953-12/1953 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - House of Prayer Quarterly Vol. 14 No. 3, 07/1955-09/1955 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Jet Magazine "Daddy Grace Buys $72,000 Mansion in N.J.", 11/05/1953 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Portrait of Daddy Grace, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    General note
    Formerly Graphic 1278
  - Portrait of Daddy Grace and identification card for Miss Mattie Scott, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Formerly Graphic 1279. description with original cataloging record "Daddy Grace; bust portrait. In identification folder of Mattie Scott of 11 Logan Circle, Washington, D.C"
  - Daddy Grace stamps, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Two Holy Convocation Ribbons, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    One ribbon reads: "27th Holy Convocation of the United House of Prayer F.A.P. Bishop C.M. Grace Founder" The other ribbons reads "Holy Convocation of the United House of Prayer for All People C.M. Grace Bishop H.L. Wohlfarth Brentwood, MD."
    Formerly Ephemera 73
  - Daddy Grace Allwater Soap wrapper, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Formerly Graphic 1304
  - Daddy Grace McCollough Pine Soap wrapper, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Formerly Graphic 1305
  - Ebony magazine, 10/1955 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Article about Sweet Daddy Grace titled "Fire hose baptism: Bishop Daddy Grace sprinkles followers on Harlem Street"
  - Ebony magazine, 04/1960 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Article about the death of Sweet Daddy Grace titled "Farewell to Daddy Grace"
- Jewelry, MS2231 Series 2; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series contains buttons, cuff links, necklaces, one red ribbon, and pins. These items have the portraits of Bishop C.M. Grace (also known as Sweet Daddy Grace), founder of the United House of Prayer for All People and Bishop Walter McCollough who become Bishop following the death of C.M. Grace.
  - Flower pin with image of Daddy Grace, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Button of young Daddy Grace labeled "His Anointed", undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Button of Daddy Grace waving, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Charm with bow and image of Daddy Grace, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Button with image of Daddy Grace, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Pin in shape of a V with image of Daddy Grace, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Heart shaped pendant with image of Daddy Grace, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Cuff links with image of Daddy McCollough, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Button with image of Daddy McCollough, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Necklace with pendant that has image of Daddy McCollough, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Square pin with image of Daddy McCollough, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Necklace with pendant with image of Daddy McCollough, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Red ribbon, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)